In the continued aftermath of the
Ukraine drone strike deep inside of
Russia on their strategic bomber fleet,
we're still trying to find out exactly
what happened. What are the
consequences? What is the relation to
the ship with this and the peace talks
that are going on in Istanbul or that
did happen in the immediate aftermath
and then where things are going now.
Part of the question that we also have
to answer is how did Ukraine do this? Is
this some spectacular Ukraine only
operation that took care of this? Was it
as some say it was the the British the
MI6 that was doing it or others are
actually saying no the US CIA also had
some involvement here? It's going to be
hard to parse some of this stuff. But
we're going to talk to somebody today
who has a a pretty good idea about how
some of these things work and that is a
first time guest on our show, John
Curyaku, a former CIA intel analyst and
operations officer and CIA
whistleblower. First of all, John, a
delight to have you on the show today.
Oh, thanks for having me. It's so much
fun. And uh I'm sorry that it's been so
long since we've seen each other. Yeah,
it has. We were talking just before we
came on air here. It was actually a
baseball game at Washington Nationals uh
in 2019 that that we had during the
championship run. So, it was the last of
the heyday. So, that was a good time at
the park. Not quite as good now, but uh
anyway, that was good. Well, listen, I I
a lot of people don't know who you are.
uh because it's the first time you've
been on our show and I wonder if you can
talk a little bit because uh you've
always been kind of a hero of mine
because of the courage that you took in
the past when some people know on our
channel anyway that that I did some
whistleblowing stuff in 2012 with the
Afghanistan war but that has been like
about 4% of the courage it took you
because it cost you something something
really serious and I wonder if you could
just kind of tell briefly about your
story.
Thank you. Well, I spent 14 almost 15
years with the CIA and uh then went to
the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
uh staff as the as the senior
investigator. But after I left the CIA,
I blew the whistle on the agency's
torture program. Uh to make a very long
story very short, uh the Obama
administration came after me, charged me
with five felonies. I was finally um
forced to take a plea to violating an
obscure law. Only the second American
ever ever charged with uh violating the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act.
And I did 23 months in a federal prison.
Zero regrets. I'd do it again tomorrow
if I had the opportunity and the the the
necessity for doing it. But here we are.
We find ourselves uh whistleblowers
outside looking in. Well, but but let's
let's get to that. I mean what what is
it that you discovered and and what did
you do uh you know first of all within
the system right I
um I was the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
and I led a series of raids that
resulted in the capture of somebody
named Abu Zuba who we believed at the
time was the number three in al-Qaeda.
Uh Abu Zuba was turned over to a secret
CIA team taken to a secret prison and he
was tortured mercilessly. He was the
first one of our high-value targets to
be tortured. And um the CIA did things
that were not approved by the Justice
Department, not approved by the
president. Uh the torture extended to
other prisoners, at least 14 that we
know of. Several were killed during the
torture sessions. And so I went on ABC
News and I said that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners. I said that
torture was official US government
policy. And I said that the torture had
been personally approved by the
president. Now, oddly,
interestingly, the Bush administration
never charged me with a crime. In fact,
they closed the case against me,
concluding that I had not committed a
crime. But the Obama administration
secretly reopened the case, charged me
with five felonies, including three
counts of espionage. I have five kids at
home, and so I'm looking at 45 years.
They offered me 30 months. I'd served
23. I took the deal
and that's that is a profound press. Uh
and and what what was the reason uh that
the Obama administration came after you
when the Bush administration against
whom you directly accused didn't Right.
Well, the reasons really are
severalfold. Um number one, I had a a
real and dangerous enemy in uh in John
Brennan. At the time, Brennan was the
deputy national security adviser. Of
course, he went on to be the CIA
director. Brenn and I, we've known each
other for 35 years. We've always hated
each other. Brennan was one of the
godfathers of the torture program. So,
he had it out for me for going public.
Uh, he said that I had aired the CIA's
Dirty Laundry in public. And Barack
Obama, let's face it, Barack Obama had a
Nixonian obsession with National
Security Leaks. Between 1917, when the
when the Espionage Act was passed into
law and 2009, three Americans were
charged with espionage for speaking to
the press. Just under Barack Obama,
eight people were charged with espionage
for speaking to the press. I think that
says it all right there.
Yeah. Well, uh, God bless you for doing
that because without that, we would
never know and and the the what has
always troubled me and I can only
imagine for you is that, you know,
Brennan had flat out lied in baldface
that we don't do that that's not
American policy, etc. And then even with
confronted with it um actually with a
number of things that were later proven
to be completely bald-faced lies. I
think the Snowden uh leaked revealed
some other things that had been and to
and he didn't serve 23 months in a
federal prison. No, he got rich. Yeah.
Yeah.
Love to see that uh come to justice one
day. And just like he seemed to wait
around for you, we'll see if maybe in
the future somebody else wants to bring
some justice. Love to see. I'm hopeful.
I'm hopeful. And and I think if
anybody's going to do it, it's going to
be this president right now.
Well, I'd like to see this president
give you a pardon is what I'd like to
see right off the bat. So, get that off
the table. Well, thank you. I I applied
for one and uh you know, I'm hopeful.
I've got some really fantastic support
in in Tucker Carlson, Judge Npalitano,
Dr. Phil, uh the former head of the uh
or the current head of the Make America
Great Again Foundation, the former US
attorney in in Utah, who who said that
my case was the template. These were his
words, the template for the Democratic
Party's policy of lawfare. And so I I'm
I'm hopeful that I'll get a fair hearing
in the White House. Well, for if it's
worth anything at all, add us on to that
list because we are in your corner as
well. I appreciate that you have done.
Well, let's get into to what's going on
right now uh in the in the US uh sphere
or at least in in the way that we're
associated with what's going on because
uh as people are aware certainly who've
been watching our show here that there
was a a big high-profile attack inside
of Russia on some of their strategic
bomber fleet. Gary's showing you some of
that video there. Uh just in terms of
the operation itself, it was reported
that it was uh 18 months in the
planning. uh lots of uh really high high
techch uh high state craft or spycraft I
guess is probably a better term
operations. It was they never were
discovered they conducted this all the
way through got it into deep inside of
enemy territory etc. But now then in the
aftermath there's some questions about
how did Ukraine pull it off. If you ask
Voodimir Zalinski he's pretty clear
where it
happened. Europe together with America
has better weapons than Russia. We also
have stronger tactical solutions. Our
operation spider web yesterday proved
that Russia must feel what its losses
mean. That is what will push it toward
diplomacy. And when Russia takes losses
in this war, it's obvious to everyone
that Ukraine is the one holding the
line. Not just for itself, but for all
of Europe.
So some have have interpreted that to
mean yeah and in fact we were doing this
with Europe not only for Europe and we
had some help in that. What is just your
assessment from the outside about and
actually let me ask you two separate
questions. First of all just in terms of
the execution of this operation how do
you view it as someone who's formerly in
the CIA?
This was a brilliant operation.
Brilliant. Whether you favor the
Ukrainians or favor the Russians, a
whole lot of planning went into the
successful execution of this operation.
Uh you think of it this way, this had to
be well actually the Ukrainians said
this was 18 months in the making. So not
only did they have to smuggle these
drones across the border into Russia,
they had to cross all 11 time zones and
get them prepositioned. You have to do
that with human beings. So this is this
is a clandestine activity. What we the
CIA used to call an operational act but
but it's multiple operational acts to
get these things in place and ready to
launch and then have the whole thing
commanded from uh Keefe. Very very
impressive operation. Now, I'm going to
disagree with with President Zilinski in
that the only people who do these kinds
of largecale operations and then don't
tell anybody about it are the Israelis.
And most of the time the Israelis do
inform us either minutes before the
operations are launched or as the
operations are being launched. There is
no possible way. There is no possible
scenario by which the Ukrainians didn't
either inform the Americans and other
Western allies that this operation was
in play or didn't have the
Americans and possibly the Brits helping
them to do this operation. It's there
are too many moving parts. It's just too
complicated. They couldn't do it on
their own.
So you you what do you say to those that
say no this is this just how good the
SBU is they can they can get that done.
What is it lead you to believe it had to
be uh either the help with somebody else
uh or that they would have said
something?
Well, you're going to need things like
like imagery for example. You're going
to need things like like um logistical
assistance. You can't do everything
yourself. Not when you're a small
country at war against a giant nuclear
power. You have to have some kind of
help. And if if you're the United States
providing billions and billions of
dollars in aid, then by God, you want to
be consulted about these things. You
don't don't want to read about these
these operations on the front page of
the Post of the Times. That's just not
the way it's done in that world. Well,
in fact, on that point, what is what
does it tell you that at least as of the
last time I checked earlier this
afternoon, uh Trump had not made any
comments about this, which I found a
little unusual because he loves to
comment on everything here. Uh and when
specifically asked Caroline Levit
yesterday afternoon was specifically
asked about the United States and what
we thought of it and what the president
thought about it and she said, "I'll let
the president ask for answer for
himself." And so, what do you make of
his silence on this? His silence tells
me that we were in on it. If if we had
been cut out, he would be furious and
maybe even a little bit embarrassed and
he would have been just beating Zilinsky
about the face and head in the media and
he hasn't been. He's been silent and to
me that says that this was that we were
at least consulted and that this was
possibly a joint operation because his
silence just you know protects the
operation. it it protects the
relationship, you know, sources and
methods as we used to say at the agency.
So, I would think that if we had been
cut out, if the president had been
embarrassed by not being consulted, he
would be jumping up and down in front of
t TV cameras uh today and yesterday. And
that hasn't been the case. And just kind
of in the larger I guess world where all
this stuff is going on here. Uh you know
the president about a week or so ago was
just blasting the Russians because they
were firing missiles and uh drones etc
into Kiev. They were in in Odessa. They
were having a lot of actions down there
etc. But then
uh number one he didn't say anything
about the Ukrainian missiles and drones
that were going in the other direction
even during that time and now hasn't
said anything here. It it it's I'm
unclear what his play is here because I
on the one hand it's like he's trying to
shame Russia, but you can't shame
Russia. They they can't be shamed for
this. No, they can't. But then but then
sometimes he's also had harsh words to
say about Zillinsky as well. So, uh what
is your take on what the president is
actually trying to get accomplished
here?
Well, Danny, I I think he's very serious
about wanting to get the two sides to
the negotiating table in Istanbul. He
has said repeatedly that he's willing to
make the trip if it will make a peace
deal more likely to be approved or even
to be negotiated in the first place. And
uh the the Ukrainians say fine, that's
great. The Russians say it's not
necessary yet. There is no peace deal,
so let them work out some of these
details first. you're right that the
Russians cannot be shamed. Um, and I
think he understands that he's already
been president for four and a half
years. So, I think he understands the
Russian mindset. I think he understands
Vladimir Putin. Um, at the same time, I
also think that the president really
believed that he could use the bully
pulpit to push the two sides together
and he's been stiff armed by Vladimir
Putin. He doesn't appreciate being stiff
armed. So, I think
that allowing these Ukrainian um
offensive operations to to go forward is
one way in which the Trump
administration can try to nudge the
Russians to the negotiating table. You
remember, I mean, we were kids, you and
I, when this was happening, but I'm sure
you've studied it. uh when the US and
the North Vietnamese began to negotiate
peace in the Paris peace talks, peace
during the the Vietnam War, that's when
some of the fiercest fighting took
place. And it's because both sides
wanted to get a leg up that they could
then negotiate away in Paris. And I
wouldn't be surprised if if both the
Russians and the Ukrainians have come to
that conclusion here that maybe you step
up operations now and then you can
negotiate it away later in Istanbul. But
you know there's it's a complicated
because you mentioned that that
President Trump doesn't like to be stiff
armed by Vladimir Putin but he's kind of
being stiff armed by Zalinsky as well.
As a matter of fact, so this is the
second uh direct conversation between
Russia and Ukraine, of course, in
Istanbul. Uh here is uh the lead
delegate for the Ukraine side, Umarov,
and coming out talking about what they
want to accomplish. And as you do, this
kind of sounds like that Umarov thinks
he's on the upper end of the power
dynamic and doesn't at all sound like
they're getting close to a peace
settlement. We've been telling Russia
for a very long time, this war must end.
and the whole world supports us in
that. We're calling for a real work to
end this war. The first necessary steps
are clear to everyone. A ceasefire,
humanitarian actions, and preparation
for a leaders
meeting. If Russia is serious about the
ending the war, it will move forward on
this. If not, international sanctions
must follow.
Okay. So, so obviously Russia is not
going to do a ceasefire first. They've
said that emphatically from day one.
Have never said anything different. So,
Umarov knows for sure that that's not
going to get done there. And then if
they don't, then we're going to going to
sanctions. So, is this an attempt and
I've heard some people suggest that it
is for the Ukraine side not to stiff arm
Trump, but to try and coers Trump into
going back on trying to find a
settlement and to instead getting back
on their train with sanctions.
Oh, I think absolutely. Yes. You know,
we shouldn't underestimate Alto
Murzalinski. He's not an idiot. Uh
sometimes we like to portray him as one,
but he really isn't. And with the Brits,
the French, the Germans, the Poles, and
a whole bunch of other allies quietly
pushing Trump to keep up those Biden era
uh programs, aid programs, military aid
programs to Ukraine. I think that
Zalinski probably has concluded that
Trump can be manipulated at least in the
short term. If the fighting is still as
serious as it is with dozens of people
being killed every day on both sides, it
allows Zilinski to then go back to Trump
and say, "You see, I would love to have
peace, but the Russians are such ogres.
They're killing our people. They're
firing rockets at civilian areas.
They're hitting apartment buildings and
parks and hospitals. The Brits and
French and Germans are with us. We know
that you want to be with us, too. That
that argument might have a little bit of
weight right now. And and you know who
else is it wants to pile on to that? Uh
there's a whole group of people in the
US led by uh Sydney Blu Sydney
Blumenthal, Richard Blumenthal, and
Lindsey Graham. And that's right, Gary,
if you can pull this one up out of the
car here. Uh Jack Keane was also pretty
uh emphatic earlier today. So the
leverage has got to be I think number
one military assistance and give them
the robust air defense systems and the
other things they desperately need. Why
is that? Because once Putin sees that
the United States is still committed to
Ukraine, he knows he can't achieve
victory. The evidence is already right
in front of us. We're 39 months into the
war, Maria. 39 long months. That's how
much time it took for us to defeat Nazi
Germany. And Putin has not succeeded. He
hasn't even taken the entire Dombas
region, which is what he wanted to take
in 2014. So, he cannot succeed if the
United States is providing military
assistance. He knows that for a fact.
Second thing, let's issue the crippling
sanctions. That is all part of the
process. Yeah, there you go with those
crippling sanctions again. But John, I
got to ask you. We've had now nearly
three and a half years of crippling
sanctions, and it has had the opposite
effect. Russia's economy is stronger
than it was, not weaker. Ours is weaker
than it was, not stronger. And Russia
keeps going forward on the battlefield.
So, come on, man. What gives? Yeah,
Danny, I if there has ever been a lesson
for the United States on sanctions, it
has been this conflict. The the Russian
The Russians have not been harmed by
sanctions. Not in any way. There are
gigantic Russian markets available in
China, in India, all over the rest of
the world. And the Chinese have had I'm
sorry, the Russians have had no problem
at all selling their oil and their
natural gas and anything else they want
to sell. Most of the world does not have
sanctions on Russia. So, we can sanction
Russia from now until kingdom come. It's
not going to harm them in any way. Just
like in Iran, the Iranians lack for
nothing. nothing. They don't need us.
They don't need Wall Street. They don't
need American investment. They have
Russian and Chinese investment and
others. So, this ought to be a lesson to
the United States that sanctions don't
work. If anything, they harm only the
poorest and most vulnerable in the
target country. We need to do something
else. Oh, I have an idea. Like maybe
negotiations. We used to joke when I was
in the CIA. We used to joke about the
George W. Bush administration and how we
had never seen anybody work so hard to
not talk to our enemies. The situation
was the same under Joe Biden. It It's
hard to to think back on an
administration where they worked so hard
to not talk to our
enemies. So maybe if we talk to them and
let the diplomats do what they're being
paid to do, we might accomplish
something that sanctions have been
unable to accomplish. Now, let me ask
you a question here kind of related to
that in terms of especially back to the
decision maker in the United States of
of President Trump. One wonders how much
how much accurate information he's being
given by I mean, let's just say the CIA
since that's what you have some
experience with in in accurately
assessing what the balance of power
between the two sides is in all the
areas you're talking about logistics,
diplomatic, manpower, etc. everything
that goes into what makes a nation state
have the power to fight and win a war.
And obviously it's off the charts in the
favor of the Russian side. Uh but
sometimes I get the idea that that
Trump hears things like uh well let me
give you an example. So, uh, the UN
ambassador for Russia, Nenzia,
ambassador Nenzia went on the UN
Security Council just a couple of days
ago and said that, "Hey, by the way,
we'd love to do diplomacy, but if not,
yeah, Gary, if you hang on, sorry, if
you can play Nenzia,
as long as Kiev tries to prolong the war
and provoke Russia by striking
residential and civilian infrastructure
on our territory, We will continue our
special military operation and destroy
objects associated with the military
potential of the KV regime and no new
anti-Russian sanctions, arm supplies to
Ukraine or other hostile steps towards
Russia will prevent the inevitable
military defeat of the Zalinski
regime. The choice is now up to Ukraine.
Peace as a result of negotiations or
inevitable defeat on the battlefield
with different conditions for ending the
conflict.
So you could say if you're Trump just
you say all right I got Zalinsky here
talking that they're going to win and
they just need all this support here and
that they can turn the tide etc. And
then I got the the Russian side over
here with Nenzia in this case saying
that no we either going to take what we
want on negotiations with this 12-point
plan they put out which is basically
terms of surrender or we're going to win
on the battlefield. Now Trump just
looking at the two of this and and any
any American for that matter can go well
they're both just you know grandstanding
etc. But if you look at the power
dynamics behind one can back up the
words and one can't. So if that was the
case then you would not want to play a
general they're trying to balance things
out but you would tell this side dude
you guys got to get off the table here
or get off your butt and get to the
table or I'm going to walk. I mean how
do you see that part?
Yeah, I have to agree with you. One of
the things too that we're not talking
about, when I say we, I mean Americans
and and especially American policy
makers, is that the the Russians have a
virtually unlimited supply of ground
troops that they can just throw into the
into the meat grinder. um not just
Russians and there have been huge losses
on the Russian side and that's because
of Russian military strategy but North
Koreans and Bellarussians and some
reports indicating Chinese who have
volunteered to go to Russia or go to the
front lines and fight on behalf of
Russia. Ukraine is a much smaller
country. They can't keep this up
forever. The Russians can keep it up
forever and Russia is a nuclear power.
So I'm going to make a guess here or
make a prediction. It's not going to be
very bold or creative, but what we're
going to see in the end is that the
Russians keep uh the disputed
territories, the Donbass, Donets,
Gluhans, Keron, they're going to keep
Crimea. Uh Ukraine will never ever be a
member of NATO. Uh they they'll likely
join the European Union eventually,
maybe even on a fast track. But I think
that the that the Russians are going to
get 90% of what they want. What the one
thing they might not get is probably the
least important and that's what the
Russians are calling dennazification of
the Ukrainian regime. Um the Ukrainians
always argue that there are no Nazis.
There may be a handful of neo-Nazis, but
not in any positions of power. I think
the Russians repeat that for propaganda
purposes. I think they'll probably be
willing to negotiate it away. But what
would they have to get in order to
negotiate that bait? because it seems to
me like one of the biggest uh
difficulties for the Ukraine side is and
Zillinsky so far been categorically
against this is that they would have to
withdraw from significant portions of
the southern three of those territories
and agree to give that up and agree to
some kind of demilitarization or
according to what Nenzia said in in
additional comments they'll go they're
going to keep fighting until they get it
one way or the other. Those are big
asks. Those are big asks and those are
unacceptable for the Ukrainians. I think
that's going to be one of those uh one
of those things on the negotiating table
that that they're going to that the both
sides are going to be stuck on. It's
going to require a lot of uh patience
and a lot of talk. Uh but that's okay.
Back back to that power dynamics though.
But the Russians don't have to give in,
right? I mean, they can just do fighting
and then they're going to lose it one
way or the other. I mean, that's that's
how I see it. Do you see it any
different?
No, I think you're exactly right. The
only thing that the that the Ukrainians
have going for them on on this issue is
that the the Russians have no interest
in occupying Ukraine. They have no
interest in occupying Kev, right?
They're only interested in those areas
of eastern and southern Ukraine that are
ethnically Russian where people speak
Russian and for the most part they want
to be a part of Russia.
They're not I don't think there's any
danger that the Russians are going to
take the whole of the country and push
all the way to the border of Poland.
That's not what the Russians are
interested in. So I think one of the 12
points was that they wanted uh the
change in the laws on the Ukraine side
that would protect Yeah, that one right
there that would protect all the full
protection of rights, freedoms, and
official language status for the Russian
speaking populations in Ukraine. And uh
that actually hearkens back to the Minsk
agreements which the Russians complained
was never put into effect. That was one
of the key parts of the Ukraine
obligations under the Minsk. It was
never executed which the Russians say
was one of the big problems here which
they will now insist upon uh with this
12point peace proposal. So the question
is uh to you where do you see this
going? Because you have these you know
categorical rejections of those key
components on the Ukraine side. the
threat and the promise rather that
Russia will keep fighting if they don't
get them. Where does this go and where
does that leave President Trump? Well, I
think that this upcoming uh meeting in
in
Istanbul already has failed before it
started. I I don't think President
Trump's going to go to Istanbul. He he
mentioned again this morning that he's
willing to go. He's willing to bring the
two sides together. He's not going to go
because they're not even close enough to
be willing to sit at the same table. So,
I think that this is a this is a loss. I
think the fighting is going to continue.
It's going to be ugly because the
weather is good and it's warmed up. So,
it's much easier to maneuver. Uh it's
much easier to to keep fighting and
pushing. So, I think we're going to keep
going through this for weeks, maybe for
months before there are are real and
substantive meetings about uh trying to
wind things down. And what if I guess in
the intervening period uh because
especially in the the northern part of
this uh this new front that that Putin
has opened up in the Sunumi area they're
starting to make some pretty big chunks
uh pretty rapid succession. So um
especially along with the the pressure
on the unrelenting pressure on the
entire eastern front and even a little
bit in the northern part with Kiank and
Kkefe areas uh it's not clear that the
Ukraine army can continue to hold out
against that that two months from now
they would be in even as good a position
as they're in right now. Yeah, I think
that's exactly right. Yeah, I'm I'm
still I used to have a I used to have a
radio show every day on Sputnik and um
and I had a TV show on RT. So in the
interest of transparency, uh I used to
work for the Russians quite happily and
um and I'm still a I'm still a member of
these list serves that they have. So
they're constantly constantly talking
about these issues. And this this
situation in in Sunumi, I think has
surprised a lot of Russians with the
relative ease with which the Russian
military has been able to uh to move.
And I think that that's a message to the
Russian leadership that the Ukrainians
are under more pressure than they're
admitting to in public. And that if the
Russians keep up the pressure, even if
they're not making huge strides, they
can put enough pressure on the Ukrainian
government that it's the Ukrainians who
then demand to go to the negotiating
table. Not the Americans, but the
Ukrainians because they're just not
going to be able to take it anymore.
Yeah. I mean, that's historically. You
mentioned the the Paris meetings in
Vietnam War uh or the the Korean
negotiations to get to the armistice. I
mean, that's kind of how it was with
that. Until the pain level got up high
enough for one or both parties, there
wasn't going to be any decisions made.
But when it did, that's what finally
drove them to uh to negotiate it. And
we'll see how this works out. Well,
listen, I really appreciate you coming
on today. It's it's been a pleasure.
Pleasure. We'll have to get together on
another baseball game pretty soon. I
can't wait. I can't wait. Looking
forward to it. It'll be great. Thanks
ever so much and we appreciate you guys
uh being with us today and uh we will
see you on the tomorrow on the next
episode of the Daniel Davis deep dive.
[Applause]
[Music]